# Ashish Panigrahi

• https://ashishpanigrahi.me

■ ashish.panigrahi@niser.ac.in • • paniash • in ashish-panigrahi99

#### About me

I am a 4<sup>th</sup> year physics student studying at the **National Institute of Science Education and Research, Bhubaneswar, India**. My interests lie in the experimental aspects of quantum technologies including quantum optics, cavity quantum-electrodynamics and quantum information processing.

Nationality: Indian

### Education

• National Institute of Science Education and Research (NISER)

Integrated Master's (CGPA till 6<sup>th</sup> semester: 9.13/10.0)

Bhubaneswar, India 2018 - 2023

• Maharishi Vidya Mandir Senior Sec. School All India Senior Secondary Certificate Examination (CBSE) - 95.6% Chennai, India May 2018

• PSG Public School
All India Secondary School Examination (CBSE) - CGPA 10

Coimbatore, India

May 2016

### Honors/Awards

• IBM Qiskit Advocate

2021

IBM Quantum

- Selected from a pool of global applicants.
- This achievement depicts a deep level of understanding with Qiskit including circuits, algorithms, simulators, qubits and noise.
- Through my contributions to the Qiskit and the quantum community, I have demonstrated an ability and commitment to educate and influence others by sharing ideas, knowledge and expertise in the field of quantum computing.

• Zonal topper

Mimamsa 2021

USER Pune

- Mimamsa 2021 IISER Pune

   Science quiz competition for undergraduates with participations from universities
  - all over the country.

     Our team became the zonal topper for the Odisha and Paschim Medinipur district (WB) zone.
- National Graduate Physics Examination (National topper)

2020

Indian Association of Physics Teachers

- Secured a score within the top 118 students among 12,000 candidates in the country.

• Department Topper (1<sup>st</sup> & 2<sup>nd</sup> year) School of Physical Sciences, NISER 2018-2020

#### • Kishore Vaigyanik Protsahan Yojana

2017

Indian Institute of Science

Bengaluru, India

 A prestigious fellowship program funded by the Department of Science and Technology of the Government of India.

#### • National Talent Search Examination

2016

National Council of Education Research and Training

New Delhi, India

- A national level scholarship program offered by the Government of India.
- It is one of the oldest and most prestigious scholarship programmes in the country.

### Academic exposure

#### • Qiskit Global Summer School

IBM Quantum

Virtual

July-August 2020

- An intensive 2 week virtual summer school on quantum computation and designing quantum circuits and algorithms using Qiskit.
- Did hands-on coding exercises to learn various quantum algorithms, pulse level control of qubits and concepts in quantum chemistry.
- Also did a project on simulating the ground energy level of LiH molecule using quantum variational eigensolver.

# • National Initiative on Undergraduate Science (Physics) Homi Bhabha Centre for Science Education, TIFR

Mumbai, Maharashtra

June 2019

- Selected as one of top 70 students in the country to participate in this camp.
- An extensive 12-day course containing lectures, independent lab work and a field trip for 2 days.
- Lecture series on quantum mechanics, quantum information theory and quantum computation, basic condensed matter physics, many body physics, astronomy and astrophysics.
- About 30 hours of independent lab work.

# Project experience

• Sixth Semester Project

Bhubaneswar, India April - July 2021

Superconducting spintronics group, NISER

- Project guide: Dr. Kartik Senapati, Reader-F, NISER
- Worked on a semester project on the topic, "Study of spin current in NM/HM bilayer and trilayer systems".
- The goal was to be able to detect spin current via a bilayer system involving Cu and Pt, using the method of electrical detection.

#### • Software Developer Internship

Remote

Quantum Brilliance, Australia

February - April 2021

- Project guide: Dr. Nariman Saadatmand, QBQE Product Manager
- Worked on QB's quantum emulator (QBQE) and enhanced functionality of its QAOA module using C++.

#### • Summer Project

Institute of Physics, Bhubaneswar

Bhubaneswar, India May - June 2019

- Project guide: Dr. Debakanta Samal, Reader-F, Institute of Physics
- Reading project on "Study on anisotropic magnetoresistance".
- Topics covered: Origin of magnetoresistance, theory of magnetoresistance in real metals using the 2-band charge carrier model, origin of anisotropic magnetoresistance, its applications and current research scenario in the field.

# Open-source contributions

#### • Qiskit Textbook

GitHub

Learn Quantum Computation using Qiskit

April 2020 - Present

- Qiskit is IBM's software development kit for building software to interact with IBM's quantum devices and OpenQASM.
- The textbook is equivalent to a university level course for learning quantum computation and beyond.
- I am a collaborator for this project and have actively contributed with over 50+ commits since April 2020.

#### Licenses & Certifications

#### • IBM Certified Associate Developer

Quantum Computation using Qiskit v0.2X

July 2021

- This certification demonstrates fundamental knowledge of quantum computing concepts and the ability to express them using the Qiskit open source software development kit (SDK).

- Shows experience in using the Qiskit SDK from the Python programming language to create and execute quantum computing programs on IBM Quantum computers and simulators.

#### • Introduction to Quantum Computing Course

Qubit by Qubit

IBM Quantum & The Coding School

October 2020 - May 2021

- Developed a foundational understanding of quantum computing, with topics including introductory linear algebra, coding with Qiskit, quantum mechanics, quantum algorithms, and quantum applications.

#### • Challenge Fall 2020 Achievement - Intermediate

**IBM** 

IBM Quantum

December 2020

- Demonstrated an ability to implement near-future quantum data structures and design a quantum game solver using Grover's algorithm.
- Showed an understanding of quantum circuits, the gates that comprise such circuits, Grover's algorithm, and qRAM (quantum random access memory) as a way to implement complex data structures.

#### • CS-191x: Quantum Mechanics and Quantum Computation

edX

University of California, Berkeley

August 2020

- Coursework involved ranging from the basics of the qubit to quantum algorithms such as Grover's, Shor's etc. to the Bloch sphere and Schrödinger's wave equation.
- Final score: 97%

# Volunteering

#### • Project Lovelace

Scientific programming problems

May 2021 - Present

- Project Lovelace is a platform to learn science through programming.
- Member of the team to add new problems and maintain the website (both frontend and backend).
- Website: https://projectlovelace.net

#### • Full-Stack Quantum Computation

Community-driven, open-source education resources

December 2020 - Present

- Part of the team as a curator of various articles on quantum technologies, submitted by volunteers.
- Website: https://fullstackquantumcomputation.tech

#### • Mentor

Avanti Fellows NGO

January - April 2019

- Duties included mentoring students from grades 11 and 12.
- My weekend work involved having a one-to-one discussion with students on physics and general advice on entrance exams.

### Technical skills

### Programming and scripting languages

C, C++, Bash, and Python (Libraries: Scipy, Numpy, Matplotlib, Sympy)

**IBM** 

## Markup languages

 $\ensuremath{\mathbb{L}} \ensuremath{\mathrm{T}} E X,$  Markdown, Groff, HTML

# ${\bf Quantum\ Frameworks}$

Qiskit, QuTiP, PennyLane

## General computing tools

Vim, git, tmux, gnuplot

